Consultant: Let's walk through what happens when a customer places an order. Can you describe the process from start to finish?
Maria Garcia: Sure. So first the customer places an order through our website or by calling our sales team. Those are the two main entry points.
Consultant: OK, so there are two entry points - web and phone. What happens immediately after the order is received?
Maria Garcia: The order goes into our ERP system automatically if it's from the website. If it's a phone order, the sales rep enters it manually. Either way, the warehouse team gets notified.
Maria Garcia: They check if we have the items in stock. This is a critical step because if we don't have inventory, the whole process changes.
Consultant: And what happens if the items are not in stock? Walk me through that path.
Maria Garcia: If it's out of stock, we notify the customer by email and give them the option to wait or cancel. If they choose to wait, we place a back-order with our supplier. The supplier usually takes 3 to 5 business days.
Consultant: Got it. And what about the happy path - when items ARE in stock?
Maria Garcia: Then the warehouse picks and packs the order. We have a pick list system. The warehouse worker scans each item as they pick it to ensure accuracy. Once everything is picked, they pack it.
Maria Garcia: After packing, shipping creates a label and schedules the pickup with our carrier. We use FedEx for domestic and DHL for international.
Consultant: Who approves the shipment? Is there a review step before it goes out?
Maria Garcia: For orders under $500, it's automatic - no approval needed. Over $500 needs manager approval. The manager gets an email notification and has to approve it in the system within 24 hours.
Consultant: What happens if the manager doesn't approve within 24 hours?
Maria Garcia: It escalates to the director. But honestly, that rarely happens. Maybe once a month. The manager usually approves same day.
Consultant: OK. And after the shipment is approved and sent out, what's the final step?
Maria Garcia: The customer gets a tracking number by email automatically. And we mark the order as fulfilled in the system. The finance team also generates an invoice at that point.
Consultant: Is there any quality check before the order is packed? Like verifying the right items were picked?
Maria Garcia: Yes, actually. After picking, there's a verification step where a second person checks the items against the order. We added this last year because we had too many wrong shipments.
Consultant: That's an important step. What's the error rate now compared to before?
Maria Garcia: We went from about 5% error rate to less than 1%. Much better. The verification takes about 5 minutes per order but it's worth it.
Consultant: Great improvement. Now, let me ask about returns. What happens when a customer wants to return an item?
Maria Garcia: Returns is actually a separate process. The customer contacts support, gets an RMA number, and ships it back. But that's handled by a different team.
Consultant: OK, we can map that separately. Let me go back to the order flow. After the invoice is generated, is there any follow-up or customer satisfaction step?
Maria Garcia: Yes. Three days after delivery, we send an automated survey. And if the customer rates below 3 stars, our customer success team reaches out personally.
Consultant: That's thorough. Now, let me verify I have this right. The main flow is: order received, inventory check, pick and pack with verification, shipping approval for large orders, ship, invoice, and follow-up survey. Does that capture it?
Maria Garcia: Yes, that's the core flow. There are some edge cases we didn't cover, like partial shipments when only some items are in stock, but the main path is what you described.
Consultant: Good. Let's discuss partial shipments briefly. How does that work?
Maria Garcia: If some items are available and some aren't, we ask the customer if they want a partial shipment now or prefer to wait for everything. If partial, we ship what we have and back-order the rest. The customer only gets charged for what we ship.
Consultant: And the back-ordered items follow the same supplier process you described earlier?
Maria Garcia: Exactly. Same 3 to 5 day supplier timeline. And they get a separate tracking number when the rest ships.
Consultant: Perfect. I think we have a good picture of the order fulfillment process. Let me summarize the key decision points: stock availability, order value threshold for approval, and partial vs full shipment.
Maria Garcia: That's right. Those are the three main decision points. And the escalation path for manager approval timeout is a fourth, even though it's rare.